Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 8 -- Letters to Franklin 1783 December-1786 Mss.B.F85inventory08
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 March 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Rush, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Composed his address before he knew the [American Philosophical] Society was to be honored with Franklin's presence; opinion of Mr. [David] Rittenhouse that there will not be the least impropriety in reading the conclusion of the oration in Franklin's presence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 March 4; L.S. 1p.; Thomson, Charles
    Congress has no objection to Dr. Franklin's accepting and retaining the picture of the King of France, presented by himself at the time of the signing of the Treaty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 March 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Congratulating Franklin on his appointment as Governor of Pennsylvania. Anxieties incident to his business relations with Mr. [Samuel] Wharton. Hopes he received the two volumes of his German work, Vermischle Schriften; would send Franklin copies of other of his publications, from time to time, if he knew an inexpensive way of forwarding them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786.] March 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Benyowsky, Countess. Baltimore
    Illness of herself and her children; death of her little daughter born in Baltimore; daily expecting the return of their ship from the Indies, when she will quit America. Enclosing a letter for Mme. Le Roy in Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 March 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Rush, Benjamin. Philadelphia
    Agreeable to his request has suppressed the conclusion of his oration ["The Influence of Physical Causes on the Moral Faculty"] in the published edition; begs permission to dedicate it to him; encloses a copy of the simple dedication he wishes to insert.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 255, note; Bigelow, IX, 304, note).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 March 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Newenham, Sir Edward. Belcamp
    Irish politics; no new taxes; pension bill much increased; corruption among the Board of Aldermen; their new speaker a Machiavelli. Prophesies that the death of Frederick of Prussia will end the Gemanic republic.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 March 13; di Milano, La Societa Patriotica. Milan
    Certificate of corresponding membership.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 March 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Arthaud, Charles. Cap François
    Sending him the first publication of a Society ["Cercle des Philadelphes"] formed for the cultivation of the Arts and Sciences; their wish to add Franklin's illustrious name to the list of members.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 March 15; A.L.S. 3p.; Le Veillard, Louis Gulliaume. Passy
    Recommending to his kindness. Mr. de la Valete. Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson's observations on Virginia, lately published, translated into French by the Abbé Morellet; Comte de Buffon vexed at having his theories contradicted. Two memoirs which have made a great sensation; M. de Cretelle's and M. du Paty's; the need of reform in French criminal law. M. de Cagliostro still in the Bastille; has published his memoirs; worthy of being printed with the Arabian Nights. Affectionate messages from Franklin's friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 March 18; A.L.S. 3p.; The Archbishop of Bordeaux. Bordeaux
    Desiring the Cross of Cincinnatus for his brother, le Comte de Champion de Cicé who commanded a vessel in the squadron of the Comte de Grasse; believes him to be the only Captain who has not received the American order. Often applies to Mme. Helvétius and the Abbés [Chalut and Arnoux] for news of Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 March 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Childs, Francis
    Safe arrival of the type; obliged to pay duty in spite of the certificates sent him by Franklin; imperfections in the type; ancient appearance of certain letters; suggested improvements.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 March 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Smith, John. Philadelphia
    Desiring him to appoint a time to examine the accounts of the estate of Robert Smith, deceased.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 March 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Remsen, Henry. New York
    Forwarding a letter from John Sargent.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 April 4; A.L.S. Thomas Lyttelton, Secretary.; The Associates of Dr. Bray
    Sending a power of attorney in order that Franklin may assist Mr.[Francis] Hopkinson in carrying out what they think best on behalf of the Associates of Dr. Bray.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 April 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Espivent de la Villesboisnet, ----
    Advantage to commerce of a mutual knowledge in France and America of the most trustworthy business houses in those two countries. Debt owing him for eight years by George Digges of Maryland; begs Franklin to remind him of this fact. Desires information as to the late transactions of the [American] Philosophical Society.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 April 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Bowdoin, James. Boston
    Sending Franklin, by Colonel Hurd, the first volume of their Academy[of Arts and Sciences] Memoirs. Thanks for Dr.[John] Jeffries's account of his aerial voyage from England to France which was read at the last meeting; will return it, agreeable to Franklin's request. Hopes to see him in Boston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 April 5; A.L.S. 4p.; Rainey, John. King's Bench Prison, London
    Account of his business ventures during the war and the large sums of paper money he deposited with the Loan Office of Philadelphia. His arrest and imprisonment due to a debt he owes a Madeira house; hears that his certificates have been attached and proceedings started against him in America; begs Franklin's interference in such an illegal piece of business.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 April 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Grand, Madame Ferdinand. Paris
    Her sorrow at Franklin's Absence lightened by the news of his improved health. Thanking him for the beautiful skins.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 April 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Wright, John. London
    Sending him [Matthew] Dobson, on Fixed Air, with Appendix by [William] Falconer. Franklin's departure from Europe deprived him of the hope of seeing him once again in this life.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 April 16; L.S. 1p.; Barker, Thomas. Edenton
    Unable to write himself owing to the wretched state of his eyes. Congratulating him on his safe arrival; hopes one day to pay his respects in person. Desires a certain receipt which Franklin took charge of for him at Passy.
    A. E. by Franklin. Extract from the proceedings at the Old Bailey in the trial of Criminals, as a text on which to amplify in his ensuring discourse.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 April 17; A.L.S. 4p.; Barclay, David. London
    American credit at a very low ebb in Europe; many just complaints of non-payment of old debts to British subjects. News of Thomas Collinson. Mr. [Matthew] Boulton and his partner, [James] Watt, deeply concerned in the improvement of steam-engines. Description of a simple method of raising water out of a well by means of a rope thrown over two wheels. Recommending the bearer to Franklin's notice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 April 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Childs, Francis
    Acknowledging his favor of the 26th ult. together with the types; desires Mr. [Richard] Bache to order for him forty reams of royal printing paper.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 April 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Mason, John. Philadelphia
    Has constructed a model for a steam boat which he desires to show him in private; desires to obtain a sufficient subscription to repeat this model on a large scale; should he receive encouragement in the above purpose, proposes to turn his attention towards making the Schuylkill navigable.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 April 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Carey, Mathew. Philadelphia
    Presenting Franklin with a copy of the debates and proceedings of the General Assembly of Pennsylvania on the subject of the bank; claims indulgence for it as America's maiden attempt. Will be glad to do any job for him, however trifling.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 April 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Benyowsky, Comtesse. Baltimore
    Her husband, greatly impoverished through loans made to Madagascar, decided to absent himself from France during M. de Castries's unfavorable administration; the efforts he is at present making to regain a part of his fortune; expects his return from Madagascar in two months; meanwhile is living in strict retirement with her children; will reserve the rest of her story for their meeting. Introducing M. Borger.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 April 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Reproaches for not having written since October. Sale of Franklin's piano-forte; disposition made of the money. Offer made by La Loge des Neuf Soeurs of a prize of six hundred livres for a Eulogy on Franklin; the exclusion of the brothers from the competition met with the strongest opposition.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 April 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Reasons for his delay in sending Franklin the roe-deer; after the severe winter just past, fears the effects on them of a long voyage; proposes waiting until September and then send a half-dozen.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 April 25; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Describes the reason why the [Crown] soap is so brittle; refers him for further particulars to Mrs. [Jane] Mecom's next letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 April 26; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Drinker, Henry
    Sending him a quantity of the Uva Ursi, which has just been gathered for his use.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 April 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Armbruster, Anthony. Germantown
    Petitioning Franklin again to take pity on his age and infirmities.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 April 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Alexander, William. Richmond
    Interested in the success of his friend [William] Temple [Franklin]; thinks Virginia is a country where much may be done with some ready money; if nothing solid offers for him, will do what he can for him in Virginia. Wrote to Petersburg concerning [Josiah] Flagg, can easily provide him with a clerkship; so far has heard nothing about him. Recommending the bearer, Mr. Jacobson, of Gothenburg.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 April 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Childs, Francis
    Account of imperfections in the type.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Benyowsky, Comtesse. Baltimore
    Rumor of the massacre of her husband together with his entire crew by the natives of Madagascar; promised to await his return in America; can do nothing until the report is confirmed or denied; begs Franklin to write to Europe for trustworthy information.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 3; A.L.S. 5p.; Ehlers, Martin
    His veneration and admiration for Franklin; takes this opportunity of his brother's departure for America to send him his work entitled Winke für Gute Fursten, as well as some other writings of which a list is appended. America's promising situation as regards religious toleration.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Roberdeau, Daniel. Alexandria
    Concerning the farm which he offered to sell him; prefers that he should get his information concerning it from an outsider; if it appears satisfactory, will be glad to treat with him about terms.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Dixon, John. Richmond
    Requesting his aid in obtaining the position of Postmaster at Richmond.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 11; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Biddle, Charles. Philadelphia
    Will wait upon him in the morning; Mr. Balliot will not leave town till the afternoon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Earl of Buchan. Kirkhill
    Introducing a mathematician and astronomer, Dr. [Walter] Minto, a gentleman likely to prove a very useful accession to the mathematical department of America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Partridge, Elizabeth. Boston
    Chagrined at not receiving one line from him in answer to her letters; sensibly affected by his coldness; desires to know if she has in any way offended him; expressions of regard and affection.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Rottenbourg, baron de
    Asking for information respecting some land in the State of New York, owned by his brother-in-law, Mr. Charles Williams, lately deceased.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 15; A.L.S. Charles Amoretti Secretary. 4p.; Patriotique, La Société. Milan
    Asks Franklin to become a corresponding member of the Society and invites the American Philosophical Society to correspond with it, particularly on the subject of agriculture.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Thomson, Charles
    Sending an extract from the contract made at Versailles, February 21, 1782, wherein are recapitulated the proceding aids granted by the King to the United States, and they are distinguished according to their different classes; discrepancy between M. [Ferdinand] Grand's account and the enclosed extract.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Proclaiming in his own name and the names of his family their respect and love for Franklin, in order that he may not feign ignorance of their sentiments.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Jay, John
    Acknowledging his letter of the 16th inst. by Mr. Whital; will immediately lay his case before M. [Diego de] Gardoqui. Thanking him for the portraits of Mr. [David] Hartley.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Jay, John
    Enclosing a letter from M. [Diego] Gardoqui on the subject of Mr. Whital's application.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786.] May 19; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Chew, Benjamin
    Invites him to dinner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, L. in 3d P. 1p.; Knox, General Henry
    Accepting the President's invitation for Thursday.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 23; A.L.S. 4p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Rejoiced at the prospect of America paying her debts. Concerning the port of Trincomali on the Island of Ceylon where his brother was Commandant; probability of England getting possession of it. Trial of the Cardinal [de Rohan]; reasons for thinking him merely the dupe of Mme. de La Motte Valois; deprived of his rank by the Pope; quotes quatrain written on the subject. Implores Franklin again to write his memoirs. Message for his grandsons. Acknowledging the ham.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Webster, Noah Jr. New York
    Concerning his project of reforming the English alphabet;encloses a plan [1p.] for reducing the orthography of the language to perfect regularity; submits it to Franklin for adoption, amendment or rejection; if he approves it, desires him to lay it before Congress; America ripe for all reforms; asks permission to dedicate his lectures to Franklin; begs him to recommend the ["Grammatical] Institute [of the English Language." 3 parts, Hartford, 1783-5].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Humphreys, Col. David. New York
    Announcing his arrival; is the bearer of many compliments and friendly message from Franklin's friends in France. News of Mr. [Thomas] Jefferson. Forwarded from London a poem by Mr. [William] Bingham. Hopes to wait upon him in a few weeks; expects to visit Boston and Mount Vernon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Hartley, David. London
    Has received no letter from Franklin since December; the newspapers never came to hand; desires to receive about once in three months a box of newspapers and Journals of Congress; begs Franklin to recommend him to a printer who will undertake the commission. Messages to friends in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Childs, Francis
    Has sent the fount of St. Augustine by Capt. Hyde; begs him to return the Philosophic, after weighing both.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Wilson, Patrick. Glasgow University
    Introducing Dr. Minto, a gentleman of professional merit and the greatest proficiency in mathematics. Messages from his father and other friends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 May 31; A.L.S. 2p.; La Rochefoucauld, Louis Alexandre, duc de
    Franklin's letter to M. [Louis Guillaume] Le Veillard gave him the greatest pleasure; delighted at the present state of affairs in America; congratulates the country on avoiding anarchy and despotism.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 June 1; A.L.S. 4p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Liberation of de Rohan; exiled to his estate in Auvergne; Count an Countess de Cagliostro likewise free; Mme. de la Motte Valois condemned to be beaten, branded, shaved and imprisoned; sentences passed on her confederates; takes exception to the sympathy lavished upon de Rohan. Account of the King's first journey; enthusiasm along his route. Asks permission to print that part of Franklin's letter which refers to the lies appearing in the English newspapers. Publication of Franklin's paper 1 on Executive Justice; combats his statement that it is better for one thousand guilty to escape than for one innocent man to be condemned.
    1 Observations on a late publication entitled Thoughts on Executive Justice, to which is added a letter containing remarks on the same work. London, I. Cadell, 1786.
    (See Ford's Franklin Bibliography, Brooklyn, 1889, p. 177.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 June 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Houdetot, Comtesse d'
    Recommending to Franklin's goodness, the bearer, one who hopes for better fortune in America than he has experienced in France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 June 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Childs, Francis
    His plan to print a pocket and family almanac for the next year; desires Franklin's advice; very busy at present; hopes by the end of the week to render him a minute and just account of the office.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 June 3; A.L.S. 3p.; B-----, A-----. Philadelphia
    Asks him to pass judgment on his invention of a boat which is unsinkable.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 June 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Nixon, William. Philadelphia
    Prevented the previous day from waiting on Franklin by a sudden attack of illness; begs him to send the promised approbation of his plan for facilitating the Latin language.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 June 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Small, Alexander. London
    Congratulating him on his safe return to America and regretting that it did not take place sooner; believes his moderation and sound judgment would have prevented many wild and extravagant acts. Highly approves of Franklin's suggested reforms of the Book of Common Prayer; great praise due their young Minister [ William Pitt]; his suppression of smuggling and the wisdom of the taxes imposed; an uninterrupted competition between Nations the true source of improvement and mutual benefit.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 June 6; A.L.S. 7p.; Paine, Thomas. Bordentown
    Introducing Mr. Hall, who carries with him the other two models for a bridge, one of wood and the other of cast iron; desires Franklin's opinion and judgement thereon; these bridges leave the river clear of the incumbrance of piers; comparison of the two models; designed the wooden bridge to span the Harlem river; suggests a bridge being created acros the Schuylkill on the plan of the iron model; hopes to see Franklin shortly and discuss the subject further.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 June 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Caswell, Richard. Kinston, North Carolina
    The Assembly passed an Act to restore Mr. [Edward] Bridgen his property.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 June 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Alexander, William. Richmond
    Concerning a piece of business undertaken by him for Franklin's old servant, Nicolas La Fargue. Requests him to deliver the securities upon La Fargue returning his obligation with an acknowledgement on the back that his trust is discharged. If his friend Billy [William Temple Franklin] has nothing to do, would be glad to see him in Richmond.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 June 12; A.L.S. 7p.; von Canstadt, Carl Friderich Schilling. Hohenweltersbach near Durlach, Suabia
    Wishes to acquire an estate in America for one of his children. Is there danger from incursion of savages? Is there spiritual and moral liberty? Suggestions to America for the encouragement of emigration. Mentions Ludwig Baisch, a Philadelphia merchant, also Messrs. Bertsch and Mayer of the same place.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 June 12; L. 2p.; von Canstadt, Carl Friderich Schilling. Hohenweltersbach near Durlach, Suabia
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780] June 14; A.N.S. 2p.; Chaumont, ------
    Account of his new invention, a kind of wig, which has the natural appearance of growing hair; honored with the approbation of the Academy, begs for a like favor from Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 June 15; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Medina, Don Luis
    Regrets not being able to dine with him; obliged to leave for New York at once to report the distressed situation of his ship.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 June 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Cocke, William. State of Franklin
    Concerning a new State separate from North Carolina to be called Franklin; 2 desires to know the date of the next meeting of Congress that the affair may be placed before them for their decision.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 260; Bigelow, IX, 318).
    2 [Afterward Tennessee.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 June 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Childs, Francis
    Sending the promised list of the imperfections in the type [2 p.]; mention of types shipped to Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 June 20; A.L.S. 4p.; Le Roy, Julien David. Paris
    The effect on his work of Franklin's interest and encouragement; sends him the results of his investigations concerning the kind of boats most suitable for navigating rivers; encloses a copy for the [American] Philosophical Society of Philadelphia; his desire to become a member and to see these studies printed in their Proceedings.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 June 21; A.L.S. 4p.; Chastellux, marquis de
    The respect and admiration with which he regards Franklin and his achievements. His motives for translating the poem of Col. Humphreys; its flattering reception by the public, but especially by the King and Queen; has taken the liberty to dedicate this work to Franklin; difficulties encountered in making such a translation. Desires to be remembered to various ladies in Philadelphia, especially to Mrs. Robert Morris, Mrs. [Samuel] Meredith, Miss Cadwalader [daughter of Dr. Thomas Cadwalader], and Mrs. [John] Craig.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 June 22; A.L.S. Nathaniel Emmons, Hezekiah Fisher, Committee. 1p.; The Town of Franklin Massachusetts
    Acknowledgment of a gift of a parish library.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786.]; A.L.S. 7p.; Coxe, Tench. Philadelphia
    Relative to American manufactures.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 June 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Webster, Noah Jr. New Haven
    Happy that his plan of reforming the alphabet meets with his approval; has engagements to lecture in Boston and Portsmouth; desires to confer with him on the subject; fixes September or October for his visit to Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1786?] June 23; A.L. in 3d. P. 1p.; Biddle, Charles
    Desires to see Mr. [John] Adams's letter, containing the objections made to delivering up the posts in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 June 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Carles, L. St. Domingo
    His brother Masons join in his request for a letter of recommendation to the Comte de la Luzerne.
    (In French. In Duplicate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 July 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Crèvecoeur, St. Jean de
    Both he and the Marquis de la Fayette disappointed at not seeing M. Dejean appointed Agent for Georgia; hopes with Franklin's influence, that he may once more dwell in his home at Detroit in Peace and security.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1786 July 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Kennedy, David. Philadelphia
    Making an appointment for a meeting of the Board of Property at Franklin's house.